# Tyson "Slava" Trotz

# Nashville, USA 571.732.5631 slavatrotz@gmail.com

GitHub: @Widewander LinkedIn: LinkedIn Portfolio: Widewander

Junior developer blending a background in language education with a passion for coding and technology. Earned a certificate in Full-Stack Web Development from Vanderbilt University bootcamp and supplementing IT education through online platforms including CodeAcademy and Brilliant. Diligent with consistent progress towards self-motivated learning as well as experienced in forming creative solutions to problems, in particular with the goal of improving user experience.

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Frontend: JavaScript, HTML5, CSS3, React, Bootstrap, React-Bootstrap

Backend: Node, Express

Databases: SQL, NoSQL, MongoDB, MySQL

Additional: Github, Tower, Dotenev

#### **LANGUAGES**

English- Native, Russian- C1, Japanese - A1, Spanish- A1

#### **PROJECTS**

#### **Profile Website**

Github: https://github.com/Widewanderer/Portfolio\_2.0 | 1

Site: https://neon-selkie-1f0b7f.netlify.app/

- Summary: React based profile website which contains personal information, skill listings, links to personal projects and their Githubs, as well as contact page.
- Role: Developed React-based project with multi-page structure. Utilized React-Bootstrap for components. Implemented Cards for projects and GitHub links. Integrated EmailJS for contact feature. Displayed skills using gridded SVG. Hosted on Netlify. Ongoing development.
- Tools: JavaScript, React, React Bootstrap, Node, Vite, EmailJs

# **Would You Rather**

Github: https://github.com/Widewanderer/Would-You-Rather-Quizes I

Site: https://wyr-3b5b304bab70.herokuapp.com/

- Summary: Survey quiz website which allows users to make a profile, create and edit quizzes, and see results of other users in real time.
- Role: Front End: Implemented survey cards for answers. Developed user profile and poll creation using MongoDB for storage. Incorporated JWT authentication for profile security.
- Tools: MERN stack, React, JavaScript, Vite, Eslint, GraphQI, Apollo Client, Node.js, MongoDB

#### **Cultured Cuisine**

Github: https://github.com/Widewanderer/CulturedCuisine I

Site: https://culturedcuisine-59da43e6096e.herokuapp.com/

- Summary: Culinary website which gives users a 'cultural experience'. Recipes are classified based on culture and accompanied by cultural information.
- Role: Developed project concept, layout, and implemented "cards" to showcase cuisines and dishes. Utilized Handlebars for dynamically generated pages, retrieving data from API to populate content. Enabled display of thousands of recipes across six cuisines using only three pages.

• Tools: Handlebars, Node, Sequelize, MySql2, Dotenv, Bootstrap Crypt,

#### **EXPERIENCE**

#### Aid Trip for Ukrainian Refugees

May 2022

Raised money, organized, and lead a small group of Russian translators on an 11 day trip to Przemysl, Poland to help Ukrainian refugees. Worked with several international organizations in quickly changing environment.

#### University of the South, Sewanee

August 2021-May 2022

Russian-Eastern European Cultural Program and House Director

Provided Russian tutoring and private lessons, organized and ran Russian Cultural programs within the school, managed the Russian House, provided Russian language atmosphere for students, did administrative work of University's Russian Department

# Campus 54, St. Petersburg, Russia

Fall 2018- Spring 2019

**English Teacher** 

Taught English as a foreign language for adults focusing primarily on advanced levels.

#### The Serendipity American Home, Vladimir, Russia

Fall 2015 - Summer 2018

**English Teacher** 

Taught both children and adults at varying levels from beginner to advanced both in classroom and private settings.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### Vanderbilt Full-stack Web-development Program

June 2023 - Dec 2023

Webdesign, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, GitHub, etc..

# University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland

Fall 2022-2023

Master's Russian-Eurasian Studies program

#### The Southern Federal University, Rostov Na Don

Fall 2021- Jan 2022

Master's Degree Program in Russian Cultural Studies

### Sewanee: The University of the South, Sewanee, TN

2010-2014

Bachelor's Degree in History, Bachelor's Degree in Russian

# Study Abroad: Smolny Institute, St. Petersburg, Russia

Summer 2011

Semester-long comprehensive study of Russian culture, language and history through locational immersion, classroom, and host family experiences.

I-to-I TEFL Summer 2015

120 hour TEFL/ TESOL online course

#### **Serendipity American Home: Training**

August 2015, 2016,2017

Month long TEFL training session and orientation